Tevis mss. LMC 2211
Lilly Library
Tevis mss.
1945-1985
Lilly Library
Tevis, Walter S.
LMC 2211
8 Boxes
The Tevis mss., 1945-1984, consist of the writings of American novelist and short story writer Walter Tevis, whose novels The Man Who Fell to Earth, The Hustler, The Color of Money, and The Queen's Gambit have been adapted for the screen.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Purchase 1999.
Biographical Note
Walter S. Tevis, 1928-1984, was an American novelist and short story writer whose novels The Man Who Fell to Earth, The Hustler, The Color of Money, and The Queen's Gambit have been adapted for the screen.
Tevis was born in San Francisco, but then moved with his family to rural Kentucky. As a child, he was placed in Stanford Children's Convalescent home for treatment of a rheumatic heart condition, where he was treated with phenobarbital, an experience he drew on in portraying Queen's Gambit protagonist Beth Harmon. After a brief stint in the Navy as a carpenter's mate on the USS Hamilton during World War II, Tevis attended the University of Kentucky, receiving his BA in English in 1949 and his MA in English in 1954. He attended the Iowa Writers' Workshop and received his MFA in creative writing in 1960. From 1965 to 1978, he taught literature and creative writing at Ohio University. He died of lung cancer in 1984. He is the author of 6 novels: The Hustler (1959), The Man Who Fell to Earth (1963), Mockingbird (1980), The Steps of the Sun (1983), The Queen's Gambit (1983), and The Color of Money (1984).
Scope and Content Note
Consists primarily of the writings of author Walter S. Tevis, 1928-1984. Tevis wrote several novels, and contributed numerous short stories and articles to magazines. A number of his novels have been adapted for film, including: The Man Who Fell to Earth, The Hustler and The Color of Money. The collection contains early manuscripts, drafts, final manuscripts, galleys and screen adaptations for most of his other longer works, although only a photocopy of The Hustler. In addition, there are typescripts of a number of his articles, a play, some poetry, as well as many of his short stories, both published and unpublished. The correspondence is small in number and consists mostly of photocopies. However, there are three original letters from science and fantasy fiction writer Fritz Leiber, and one each from authors E.L. Doctorow and Herbert Gold.
The Writings are arranged as follows: Published novels, unpublished novels, articles, childhood writings, literary criticism, a play, poetry, published book of short stories, other published short stories, unpublished short stories, and fragments of works. Photocopies of articles about Tevis and his writings complete the collection.
Arrangement/Organization
Arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings.
Authors, American; World War, 1939-1945 --Personal narratives, American.; Soldiers --United States --Correspondence.; Motion picture film; Tevis, Walter S.; Leiber, Fritz, 1910-; Doctorow, E. L., 1931-; Gold, Herbert, 1924-
- Correspondence
  - Nine letters written by Tevis to his family while serving in the United States Navy during World War II, 1945-1946; including two pages of sketches by Tevis drawn at this time (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence arranged by correspondent (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clune, Henry W. Letters to Walter S. Tevis and, Oct 8, 1974; Nov 4, 1974; (both photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Doctorow, Edgar Lawrence. Letter to Anne Goodman Freedgood (editor), Jan 12, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gold, Herbert. Letter to Eleanora (Walker) Tevis and Walter S. Tevis, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Guthrie, A. B. Letter to Walter S. Tevis, Jun 1, 1952; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Leiber, Fritz. Letter to Eleanora (Walker) Tevis, Apr. 18, 1980; (incomplete) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Leiber, Fritz. Letters to Eleanora (Walker) Tevis and Walter S. Tevis and, Oct 24, 1980; Jan 17, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Littauer, Kenneth P. Letter to Walter S. Tevis, Jan 22, 1957; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mills, Robert Park. Letter to Walter S. Tevis, May 27, 1975; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Riordan, Marianna. Letter to Walter S. Tevis, Jun 16, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Schickel, Richard. Letter to Walter S. Tevis, May 21, 1976; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Eleanora (Walker). Letter to Walter S. Tevis, May 21, 1976; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to British Lion Films, Ltd., Jun 2, 1975; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to W.B. Carnochan, Nov 8, 1981; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Circus Magazine, Dec 30, 1975; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Larry Jordan, ca. 1978-1979; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Robert P. Mills, Aug 1, 1979; Oct 30, 1978; (photocopy of August 1, 1979) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Betty A. Prashker and Patrick LoBrutto, Oct 15, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Marianna Riordan, Jun 25, 1983; (copy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tevis, Walter S. Letter to Buz Wyeth (?), Oct 27, 1960; (photocopy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings
  Scope and Contents
  The Writings are arranged as follows: Novels - published and unpublished; articles; childhood writings; literary criticism; plays; poetry; short stories - published and unpublished; and fragments of works. Three magazines containing articles and photocopies of several articles all concerning Tevis and his writings complete the collection.
  - Novels
    Published novels are arranged by various forms of the book from original manuscript to drafts to galleys, followed by related notes, outlines, synopses, ending with alternate forms of the book, such as plays, screenplays or teleplays. Drafts and related materials of unpublished novels are filed at the end of this section.
    - The Color of Money (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Original typescript (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
      - Author's copy of final draft, Feb 4, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      - Copy #3, Feb 12, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      - Author's final copy, Feb 13, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      - Draft pages (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
      - Dialogue between The Color of Money and Walter S. Tevis (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Eddie's background (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Outlines of chapters (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
      - Notes (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Notebooks (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Screenplay, draft, Dec 19, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Screenplay, draft, Sep 26, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Screenplay, by Richard Price, Rev., Dec 30, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Screenplay, incomplete (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Screenplay, final., 2 Copies (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - The Hustler (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
      - Photocopy of typescript (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - The Man Who Fell to Earth (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
      - Original typescript (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
      - Original typescript for Oxford University Press Alpha edition (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Epigraphs (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Screenplay by Dick Wheelwright (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Screenplay - suggestions and notes (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Mockingbird (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Earliest version (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Two early versions, one date, ca. Oct. 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Opening and revision to Reader (earlier title) (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Part Two: Spofforth. Early version of Chapter 3 and early page of Spofforth (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Original typescript (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Drafts (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
      - Final manuscript (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
      - Final manuscripts, 2 Copies (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
      - Copy edited version (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
      - Galleys (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
      - Notes (Box 3, Folder 9)
        General
        1)"Harrison [Starr, film producer] says..."; 2) "A novel is a story and a story has direction...."
      - Play, adapted for Readers Theatre, Bowling Green State University, by Lois A. Cheney (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Screenplay, Written for the Television Laboratory at WNET/THIRTEEN, 2 Copies (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - The Queen's Gambit (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      - Original manuscript (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
      - Synopsis (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Corrected rough draft, Apr 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
      - Author's copy, final draft, Jun 30, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
      - Early manuscript (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Misc. draft pages, marked "Disorderly pages" and "various segments" (Box 4, Folder 9-15)
      - Printer's copy (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Printer's copy (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
      - Master proofs:, Sep 21, 1982; Oct 25, 1982; Oct 27, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
      - Setting copy (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
      - Chessbook, typescript of early form of novel (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Dialogue between The Queen's Gambit and Tevis (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Eleanor Walker's notes on manuscript (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Notes and emendations (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Outline for Chess in America, nonfiction, precedes The Queen's Gambit; and single page of Vegas (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Pandolfini/Tevis consultation notes (Bruce Pandolfini, National Master, proof read manuscript for chess errors) (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Synopsis (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Motion picture treatment (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Screenplay, several corrected typescripts (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
    - The Steps of the Sun (working title: Belson) (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
      - Original manuscript (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
      - Second draft and partial second draft (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
      - Final draft and copy (Box 6, Folder 6-10)
      - Draft pages (Box 6, Folder 11-14)
      - Printer's copy (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Printer's copy (cont.) (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Galleys (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
      - Chapter 6 altered and published in OMNI Magazine (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Chinese characters for Belson's name (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Notes (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Outline (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Synopsis (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Motion Picture treatment (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - And So I Die Next (unpublished) (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
      - Manuscript (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Notes (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Outline (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Wit's End/Drunk (unpublished) (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Photocopy of manuscript (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Draft pages (Box 7, Folder 16-19)
      - Outline (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Articles
    - How to Play Straight Pool (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - The New Young Ones (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Three untitled, partial articles, all concerning pool (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Photocopies of articles from magazines (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Childhood Writings
    - Stories and a poem (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Literary Criticism
    - Written for classes at the University of Kentucky and The Iowa Writers Workshop (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Analysis from a Paragraph William Faulkner's That Evening Sun Go Down (Iowa) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Arthur Hobson Quinn on Poe (Kentucky) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - The Darling Room: Tennyson and the Theme of Isolation (Iowa?) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Grammar and Language in April Inventory by W.D. Snodgrass (Iowa?) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Gustave Flaubert: The Legend of St. Julian the Hospitaller (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Impinged Lives in William Faulkner's The Evening Sun Go Down. (Iowa), Aug. 5, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Pity This Busy Monster, Manunkind by e.e. cummings: A Parody of Discourse (Iowa) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - The Poetical Reputation of Andrew Marvell: A Reappraisal. (Kentucky), Aug. 2, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - The Problem of Obscurity in Five Books by Joseph Conrad (Iowa) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - Spiller and Lawrence on Cooper. (Kentucky), July 8, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
      - An Undertow in one of V.L. Parrington's Main Currents and a Reading List for English 216C. (Kentucky), June 20, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
  - Play
    - Spending a Day With Mother (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Poetry
    - Includes the following poems: (Box 7, Folder 29)
      Dostoevsky, Tolstoy, Russian Roulette, Me
      Drunk in the Garden
      Drunk Poem Number One
      February Twenty-One, Nineteen Seventy Nine
      The Game and the Play of Chess
      A Gratefully Recovering Alcoholic: First Things First, Easy Does It, One Day At a Time
      The Hustler
      Jamie After Sixteen Years
      Mother's Visit
      My Name is Bobby and I Came To Play
      Nineteen Seventy Eight
      On Metaphysics: With a Traitor
      A Poem for Madeleyn Who Moves Fast
      Poem: With Electrodes on My Head
      Sci-Fi Poem Book
      The Spirit Moves Deeply Toward Whiskey
      The Spirit Moves Fearfully Toward Sobriety
      Thirteen Thirty Eight Fortieth Avenue (appended to: The Hustler)
      To Julie
      Villanelle for H. Chovnik
      A Way Out
      Win a Few Lose a Few
  - Short Stories
    - Far From Home (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Far From Home (published collection of short stories)., title: The Apotheosis of Myra; title: The Big Bounce;; title: Daddy;; title: Echo;; title: Out of Luck;; title: Rent Control;; title: The Scholar's Disciple;; title: Sitting in Limbo;; title: A Visit from Mother (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
      - Copy edited manuscript (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Galleys (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
    - Other published short stories (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
      - The Actors (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - The King is Dead (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - The Machine That Hustled Pool (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - The Man from Budapest (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - A Short Ride in the Dark (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - Sucker's Game (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Photocopies of various stories published in magazines (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Unpublished short stories (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - The Albatross (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Big Man from the West Coast (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - Cowards Die Many Times (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - The Double Crossed Wire (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - Gangster Cat (Box 8, Folder 25)
      - The Gorilla System (Box 8, Folder 26)
      - The Kingdom of Heaven (Box 8, Folder 27)
      - Konraq (Box 8, Folder 28)
      - Moriae Encomium (Box 8, Folder 29)
      - My Name is Brown, Sir (Box 8, Folder 30)
      - Royal Flush (Box 8, Folder 31)
      - The Second Coming (Box 8, Folder 32)
      - A Small Town Affair (Box 8, Folder 33)
      - Stop! (Box 8, Folder 34)
      - A Thing of Beauty (Box 8, Folder 35)
      - Turnip Island (Box 8, Folder 36)
      - Upright Coach (Box 8, Folder 37)
      - The Weather is Uncertain (Box 8, Folder 38)
      - When Last I Saw You (Box 8, Folder 39)
      - Untitled (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Fragments of works
    - Blunt Instrument (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Burton (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Crippled for Life (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - The Disillusionment of Peter Baradolph (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Fidelity (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Flight (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - The Homeless (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Iago (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Mafia Bees (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - The Man Himself (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Melba on Burton (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Salt 17 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - School in Nowhere (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Transbox to Porbyx (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Untitled fragments (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Photocopies of articles about Tevis and book reviews (Box 8, Folder 56-57)
    - Three magazines, with articles about Tevis (Box 8, Folder 58)
      - Chess: A Novel Idea, and an excerpt from The Queen's Gambit. Chess Life, May 1983 (Box 8, Folder 58)
      - Toasting the Best of Times, The Courier-Journal Magazine, Jan 27, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 58)
      - Walter Tevis is Hustling Again, Sunday Plain Dealer Magazine, May 21, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 58)